Chapter 3: Playing Chess, Pt 2 — Pawn Takes Queen

A/N: Apologies for the delay.

Leirad: Harry does not know the Summoning Charm, which Canon Harry doesn't learn until GoF.

The white king's pawn ground forwards two places.

"First. Who exactly are you?"

Professor Quirrell's shoulders straightened, and he appeared to consider the question.

"I am Professor Quirinus Quirrell, Lord David Monroe, Sir Jeremy Jaffe, Doctor Artadus Bunting, and a handful of others."

Professor Quirrell's gaze grew distant.

"As for how I came to be what I am... well. You are familiar, I know, with the Dark Art called Horcrux."

Harry nodded. He'd given some thought to how that spell could be used, if it could be engineered to use some different source for the death-burst, such as a magical creature. If a phoenix's regeneration superseded the power of a magical sacrifice, that was one potential option...

"I was David Monroe, defender of Britain. The Dark Lord was tearing the country apart, and if Magical Britain fell the rest of the world would surely follow. The Order could not hope to defeat Voldemort." The voice grew bitter. "I thought myself better suited, a Slytherin to counter a Slytherin."

Monroe's eyes narrowed.

"I was naïve. Albus Dumbledore was the only living wizard who could truly be called Voldemort's better, on top of that wielding the Hallowed Wand, called the Only One He Ever Feared. At no point was he anywhere near enough to match the terror that was the Dark Lord."

The beginnings of a sneer were playing about his face.

"I was a fool, a complete and utter fool. You wonder where I learnt my wizardry, boy? I pierced Salazar's Chamber, I spoke to his snake, I studied the Forgotten Arts. And when I was finished, I thanked the Basilisk courteously and left. I returned to the Chamber in my final year, to give my final thanks and goodbyes."

Then his voice was no longer contained, but cracked and vicious.

"I found the Basilisk's mouldering corpse! Beside it was a Penseive with a memory of Riddle gloating that he had killed the creature that only ever wished to help him, that Salazar had left as an unconditional gift to his heirs!" The aura of danger around Quirrell focussed into a pain in Harry's scar, and a light wind fluttered the elder wizard's robes around him.

"I make no claim to be a good person, Mr. Potter, but I like to think that I am not so empty as Riddle was even as a child."

A black knight fell from its granite horse.

Quirrell clenched a withered fist.

"And yet, I thought I could stand against Voldemort. Do you know what his plan truly was, boy?" he spat. "I learned of it later; you will understand soon enough. The Dark Lord was playing. I was powerful enough, courtesy of Slytherin's Monster, but utterly, hopelessly outmatched. Voldemort could have taken over Magical Britain within a week. But he had been bored, he was having fun... His plan was to allow me, David Monroe, to seemingly finally defeat him and take over Britain, and thence the world. But when he learned of the prophecy, he had no further use for me."

Quirrell sacrificed a pawn to the white queen.

He sighed. "In the beginning, I thought I could redeem Slytherin house. It says something rather profound that one thing I shared with the Dark Lord was an intense dislike of bullies. I would change that, become the Slytherin against whom all others would be measured." A short, bitter laugh. "And yet I was always a pawn of the Dark Lord, as I discovered one Hallowe'en."

Harry gave a small, involuntary step back at that. The tension had been rising, and Quirrell looked coldly, calmly furious. Harry had the uncomfortable notion that this was what his friends felt when he was angry.

"I knew the prophecy, and I had received intelligence that the Dark Lord intended to attack your home. I arrived on the scene to find James dead on the threshold, Lily fallen having tried desperately to save you." A touch of sorrow reached Quirrell's eyes, such an expression as Harry had rarely seen on him. "The Dark Lord used Lily's death to perform the Horcrux spell upon you. He planned, I believe, to thus destroy all but a remnant of you and remove the difference between your spirits, and set you up as a puppet instead of me. It did not end well for him."

"The resonance?"

"Yes. I am given to understand that the resonance is a side-effect of prophecy. As the Dark Lord wrought his spell, the turbulence began to burn him from the inside out. Just as I arrived, Riddle counterspelled my attempt at shielding as easily as I overwhelmed those bullies in the hallway, and then he cast aside his wand and tried to possess me, hoping to protect himself."

The white king moved to hide behind a pawn.

" I- I was caught up by the Horcrux spell. As he was trying to possess me, it was not the traditional overwrite, but a massive input of all that Riddle was..."

Quirrell trailed off, and took a deep breath. He looked old, and tired, and miserable. The Defence Professor had never shown such emotion in all the time Harry had known him. He gave Harry a measuring look.

"Mr. Potter... Harry. This- this is not a pleasant story, especially for you. This is one of the things I see when the life-eaters approach. And yet I know that you have seen things most will have the luxury never to see. You are no ordinary child. Even so, I will not blame you if you refuse to see this."

A lump rose in Harry's throat. It was the first time, the first time Professor Quirrell had ever used his first name.

From the dark robes came a small, grey stone bowl etched with odd runes, which settled on a conjured desk. Quirrell placed his wand to his temple and drew from it a thread of what looked like something between molten lead and Patronus light, which settled in the bowl, glowing faintly blue.

"It iss ssafe."

Harry swallowed, remembering the last Penseive memory he'd seen, Dumbledore losing his brother. He placed his hands on either side of the bowl, and leaned down until he fell into the memory.

The nursery was warm and brightly-lit and airy, yet it held a chill reminiscent of Dementors. Lord Voldemort stood over the corpse of a red-haired woman, tall and pale and terrible, tracing a spiral pattern in the air. The spiral was neither dark nor bright, no colour human eyes should have received, no colour a human brain could describe - it looked like the colour of something entirely colourless, with nothing behind it whatsoever, the same colour as what Harry saw out of his elbow.

Harry realised with a jolt that this was in part Voldemort's memory.

A small part of Harry noted that the Penseive showed more detail than Voldemort could possibly see, let alone remember, and wondered how to exploit that ability.

Black hatred surged in Harry as the Dark Lord touched his wand to Lily Potter's forehead and raised it to the swirling spiral of nothingness.

Lord Voldemort hissed in cadences older than Latin, "Sozdomai, ton phrenon emou sozdo..."

The beginning and ends of the spiral of nothingness glowed stark white.

The bone-white wand rose, touched the infant's head-

And then the far wall was torn away, a gust of wind blew freezing droplets into the warm room, and a man dismounted a broomstick and drew his wand in one smooth motion.

"I truly thought I might save them," came the soft voice of the modern-day Monroe from behind Harry.

Harry jumped and turned.

"I am... very sorry for what happened this night."

Harry nodded, not trusting himself to speak.

The young Monroe rushed towards the screaming Dark Lord, opening his mouth to chant Shield Charms-

Voldemort slashed his wand and released it mid-swing. Monroe's shields were torn away like so much tissue paper, the Dark Lord vanished in a black swirl, and Monroe collapsed, holding his hands to his bleeding head and screaming, screaming in two tones, alternately deep and human and high-pitched and demonic-

The spiral of nothingness flashed every colour and burst, setting every hair on Harry's neck on end and-

The nursery vanished.

The darkness coiled around him, and David was dead, he knew he was dead, life could not possibly contain such pain. Suddenly his head rushed, and he was assaulted with a thousand books, a thousand libraries, everything that was the Dark Lord, and it burned.

The scene changed.

The scraggly little rabbit was growing old. It had a bite taken out of one ear and its fur was falling out and most of its tail was long gone, but Billy Stubbs doted on it. It didn't take Legilimency to know that it was the only thing left in the world that yet loved Billy.

One day, Billy had shoved Tom Riddle at the dinner table, had taken the last of his favourite food, and when Tom had protested Billy had hit him, and called him a freak.

And Tom had listened to Billy's screams, and his sobs, and more screams every night when he had nightmares (always inexplicably vivid and consistent), after the rabbit was found hanging by its neck from the rafters, and smiled.

The scene changed.

"Go on, then!" bellowed the small, balding man. "Go on then, Tom! Kill me! Martyr me! I've lived a good life. More than anyone could say for you. You're pathetic. I'm not scared of you."

"Is that so, Yermy?" hissed a voice that might have come from the whistling wind or the crackling fires consuming the bolt-hole. "Is that so?" He waved a skeletal, spidery hand, and the Disillusioned, Silenced forms of three women were revealed behind him.

"No," whispered the old man, "No, no, NO-"

The scene changed.

The Dark Lord reappeared in the nursery, staggering.

Then the scene paused, and Professor Quirrell turned to Harry.

"The Dark Lord unwittingly imprinted his being onto me," intoned the modern Monroe grimly. His voice took on something like a professorial tone, though it was still strained. "Mr. Potter, when you heard of the Horcrux spell, what was your first thought?"

It took him some effort, through the numbing pain, horror and revulsion, but Harry thought back. "To improve it."

"And this Lord Voldemort had done. He had formed his greatest creation: an improved Horcrux. Legends suggest this may have been the original form of the spell. Regardless, each Horcrux granted him what might be called a soul: a constant non-physical embodiment of his being."

Something of a Riddle. "One Horcrux buried in solid rock," muttered Harry heavily, "One Horcrux sunk to the depths of the ocean. One Horcrux dropped into the Earth's mantle. One Horcrux flying invisibly in the sky. And one drifting forever through space, the Pioneer Plaque."

That wasn't quite as bad as it could be. There might be some way to track them, somehow, through the magical link that must surely exist in some form... and NASA knew exactly where the Probe was...

Quirrell seemed to gather himself, and his gaze turned sharp. "If you are considering the practicalities of a great quest to hunt down the fragments of the Dark Lord's soul, know that the spell has no great cost, merely a murder."

"I see," said Harry hollowly. "The Dark Lord made a Horcrux every time he murdered someone. Pebbles tossed in the sea, grains of sand..."

"Mr. Potter, this puzzle," Quirrell gestured to the tableau, "is soluble with your knowledge of magic. The Dark Lord Voldemort releases his possession and reappears before you, briefly dazed, and you are able to Stun him before he recovers. He has thousands of Greater Horcruxes hidden even he knows not where. If you kill him, he will return, and he will wreak the most terrible vengeance upon you. What do you do?"

Harry saw the solution instantly. What he'd been calling his dark side was just the echoes of the Dark Lord in his mind, and when he'd asked it what it thought of death...

The Dark Lord Voldemort had held such a terror of death that he had seized on his first solution and implemented it again and again, flinching away from the uncomfortable thought that it might be fallible.

A Muggle security analyst would call that fencepost security, like building a single mile-high fencepost in the middle of the desert. Nobody would try to climb it - they'd simply walk around it.

No number of Horcruxes would ever help Frank and Alice Longbottom. Thirty minutes under the Cruciatus Curse, and the Dark Lord would be gone forever. Or, even better, hit him with an Obliviate hard enough to make him forget his own name. The greatest Dark Lord in centuries could be destroyed by a first-year of Hogwarts.

"You Memory-Charmed him so hard that he lost his entire episodic memory?"

Professor Quirrell shook his head. "That would have been the better solution, but no. Not quite." His eyes were stony and still, his face seeming carven from ice. "Words cannot possibly express my feeling in that instant. Monroe's righteous rage, Riddle's cold fury..."

The memory-Monroe snatched the Dark Lord's fallen wand and hissed, "Stupefy." The scene froze again.

"Using two wands is dangerously unpredictable and inefficient, but I was beyond all reason." The words were quiet. "I had hated Riddle before. He murdered my entire House, and some he did not grant the mercy of the Killing Curse. I arrived too late, held them as they died... and yet never before I received his Horcrux spell did I feel such loathing."

The younger Monroe aimed two wands at the Dark Lord and shrieked, "CRUCIO!"

Harry watched, almost unseeing, as the Dark Lord writhed and twitched under the wands of Harry's friend's younger self.

It wasn't right, it shouldn't have happened, not even to him, not to anyone.

Quirrell's voice was soft, lilting, and Harry felt sick as he realised that this was most likely the best part of the memory for Quirrell.

"Before you judge me too harshly, Harry, listen. This is my worst memory, the worst memory. This night, I was made to be like the Dark Lord. Riddle had once tried to be happy. He was nothing if not sensible. He spent a great deal of effort trying to help people. He was Alexander Chernyshov, he liberated some tiny hellhole and its inhabitants wept tears of gratitude. For him, it felt like nothing in particular." Quirrell's voice dripped contempt. "I can still remember how it used to feel to help people, call to mind the warm glow. Sometimes I still feel it, to some degree. That plain indifference is the Dark Lord's curse, worse than any magic I or any other could cast on him. And that is what he gave to me. And that is how I cast one of the most dreadful curses and feel nothing."

Harry was frozen, he had no idea what to say, no idea what to think.

"I will not show you the worst of Riddle's atrocities. I am not a soft-hearted man, Mr. Potter, but sometimes I still wake from nightmares about what happened to Amy Benson and Dennis Bishop, when the Dark Lord was nine years old."

The memory faded, and Harry was standing once more on a tile of cool stone.

Harry wiped the sweat from his forehead. There would be time to process all of this later, time to rage and weep later. For now he could use his Occlumency and pretend to be someone impartial. He needed to learn as much as he could.

"What was the Dark Lord actually planning?"

The grim, stony expression remained. "The Dark Lord planned to have David Monroe appear to kill him, then touch a Horcrux and become a puppet leader. As for why he did not effect this sooner... past emotions are difficult to untangle from the mess of Riddle's memories, but I believe he was simply enjoying the game too much. He felt invulnerable, and fell too deeply into the role he was playing. Dumbledore, you see, has not a Slytherin bone in his entire body, and yet he tries because he must. Dumbledore brings to his task the Elder Wand, the Line of Merlin Unbroken, a phoenix, some source of foreknowledge, magic beyond any seen for three hundred years, intelligence, dedication, and an utter lack of talent. For that reason, he is marvellously difficult to predict."

Harry's throat felt dry. Somewhere, the Sorting Hat was screaming at him. The thought had finally occurred to Harry that his unreasonable hatred of Dumbledore had come from the imprint of the Dark Lord, and indeed, when he'd queried his dark side he'd found burning hatred and contempt. I think, said Hufflepuff, you owe someone a very big apology.

Quirrell's lips thinned. "The Dark Lord's little game broke five of my rules at first count, which is generally too much no matter how much fun one might be having, but I suppose he thought he stood to lose little."

The white king was hemmed in now.

"Another question, Professor. Who killed Hermione? The wards identified it as you." Please don't let it have been you, if you killed Hermione I want to believe you killed Hermione, please don't let it have been you...

Professor Quirrell set his teeth. "I did not succeed in what I did to the Dark Lord, Mr. Potter. "

"Of course you didn't. It would be purest optimism to assume the Dark Lord is no longer a threat, just because he was Cruciated into insanity and burned to a crisp..."

"The Dark Lord was the greatest Occlumens in all recorded history. Merlin himself would have been unable to pierce his mind. Somehow, he managed to ignore the curse long enough to fake catatonia. Like a fool, I approached, and he seized his wand and poured the scraps of his magic into a blasting curse that vaporised my body and blew the roof off Godric's Hollow, but burned Voldemort as well. He expired shortly thereafter. As a partial copy of the Dark Lord, I was protected by the Horcruxes. It was then that I found that the great creation was imperfect. I could not float free, but was shackled to Horcruxes that the Dark Lord had hidden even from his own eyes. I was trapped amidst the stars for years. I did consider going mad, and sometimes wonder that I might have. The stars were my greatest comfort, for it is their nature too to burn, lonely, in the night."

The blank look on the Defence Professor's face was unnerving. "Eventually, almost two years ago, a man named Quirinus Quirrell found a Horcrux hidden in the folly of Riddle's youth, when he hoped for immortality by hiding lesser Horcruxes behind tests of skill and might. Quirrell was a Muggleborn adventurer, come to seek his fortune, with a vague fallback plan of teaching Muggle Studies at Hogwarts. I had more presence of mind than the Dark Lord's shade, and seized control. I suppose I shall owe Mr. Quirrell an apology when I can create a new body with the Stone, though this is something different from true possession and I doubt he will be permanently harmed."

A pang of sympathy for the original Quirrell tore through Harry, although he supposed that it was technically justified to steal someone's body for a few years, to escape eternity trapped alone with Voldemort. "So Voldemort..."

Professor Quirrell sighed, and he seemed to diminish somehow. "Nobody is immune to mistakes, Mr. Potter." He traced a symbol in the air with one unbroken finger movement, a triangle containing a line bisecting a circle.

"Thinking the Dark Lord truly lost, I sought the Resurrection Stone when you showed me its symbol. I found it upon a ring that Voldemort had long ago made into a Horcrux - by sheer chance, he had targeted the ring, not the Stone - and hidden in the ruins of his grandparents' home."

The foul bird in the corner fluttered its wings.

"In retrospect, I ought to have burned the place to the ground with Fiendfyre and then sought the Hallow, which may have escaped even that curse, and yet I learned too late the value of unsubtlety. Some curses, such as the Parselmouth curse, are more effective and easier to cast if they bind the caster as well. The Dark Lord, clever even as a youth, had cursed the ring to compel any who came upon it to covet it, to protect it, to wish to own and use it for themselves, bypassing any shield, and had made up for such a powerful effect by having it apply to himself tenfold."

A sick feeling was growing in the pit of Harry's stomach again. I'm sorry, Headmaster. "The curse identified you as the caster and overwhelmed you. You made the Resurrection Stone your Horcrux, and now, with its magic, the Dark Lord's shade can move freely. Voldemort possessed Professor Sprout, and framed Hermione, and set the troll on her."

Professor Quirrell nodded gravely. "The Dark Lord is half-mad, Mr. Potter, but still not stupid. He strikes blindly at you. He Transfigured the troll from the cloak I was wearing on the day the Headmaster identified me to the wards, and used an old ritual to transfer a true troll's magic to it."

Harry clenched a fist. "What way can you conceive to eliminate the Dark Lord permanently, Professor?"

"Further Cruciation. Obliviation. The Draught of Living Death. The Dementor's Kiss may suffice, although I doubt it. Dropping his wand into the pit of Azkaban, although that would only affect the Dark Lord if he had a body, and the wand would swiftly be broken down by the Dementors. Invoking some sort of truly greater, insurmountable magical effect may work, such that from that day forward the world would be without the Dark Lord... in fact, I think there may be something quite close by."

The white king was alone on the board, now.

"First we heal you, Professor. Then we resurrect Hermione, and then we make sure the Dark Lord never mildly irritates us again."

Professor Quirrell laughed grimly, and behind him, the bird of black fire spread its wings and gave a warped, crackling cry.

"And of course, Mr. Potter, what I have ssaid in thiss room iss no lie: am Horcruxx-copy of Dark Lord imprinted on pureblood-lord-hero, greater Horcruxxxesss presserve Dark Lord copiess ssuch asss mysself, Dark Lord livess, half-mad, he attacked girl-child friend."

The cry came once more, louder.

Harry nodded curtly, and stepped onto the back rank, trapping the king. "Checkmate."

The white king's crown fell at his feet, and the next door swung open.

Chapter 6: Interlude — Conspiracy Theories

Professor Quirrell threw away his wand as though it had caught fire, lurched away from Harry, and blurred down into his Animagus form.

Harry pressed his hands over his eyes, waiting for the pain to fade.

We did it. Professor Quirrell has the Stone.

Harry exhaled slowly. Transfiguration was powerful enough already, and now they had the power to make it permanent.

You couldn't Transfigure specific people, of course, and nor could you Transfigure lost books, but bizarrely enough you didn't need perfect knowledge of what you were making to Transfigure it - Professor McGonagall didn't have an encyclopaedic knowledge of porcine biology, and Harry didn't know the precise specifics of a rocket. In fact, even steel was complicated: there were different sorts of steel with different amounts of carbon and other additives. Transfiguration could clearly get information from somewhere that wasn't the caster's brain.

Harry opened his eyes and saw for the first time his surroundings.

The floor was worn and grey with dust, stained oddly brown in places. A slashed painting hung crookedly above a ruined fireplace, cold ashes spilling out over the floor. Nearby was a chair with three legs torn off. The room looked like it had been shredded. The whole place felt uneasy, like the quiet aftermath of a storm.

Harry suppressed a shiver. Ahem, said Hufflepuff, it might actually be a good idea to be afraid of magical haunted houses.

The snake lay unconscious on the dusty floor, a sealed silver pouch behind it. Harry couldn't Innervate Professor Quirrell, and he wasn't sure that it was possible to shake a snake awake. Absently, Harry wondered how the rules for Animagus transformations worked - if you touched the Stone to an Animagus, were they trapped forever? What happened if you turned into an Animagus while holding an indestructible magical artefact, then died?

It was probably a good idea to start planning the best applications of the Stone, so Harry closed his eyes and thought.

Transfiguration seemed even more strange the more that Harry considered it. The universe, or the Source of Magic, or whatever, would obligingly fill in all the necessary information about nerve configurations and biochemistry and such if you said give me a working pig from scratch, but not if you said give me a working Hermione Granger from scratch. It would give you all the information you needed, and which you absolutely didn't already know, to Transfigure a computer, but not to Transfigure a nanofactory. That didn't necessarily mean that nanofactories were impossible - Harry had tried to Transfigure a computer slightly more powerful than modern-day technology, and it hadn't worked either.

Harry had been slightly disturbed by the idea that a fully living pig had popped into being, then vanished. He had wondered what would happen if you tried to Transfigure a generic human like McGonagall had Transfigured a generic pig, but had dismissed the experiment as hideously unethical.

That pig had known how to stand up, so its brain had worked perfectly well. Could it have just been some sort of Platonic ideal pig? Probably not, since it would be perfectly possible to Transfigure, say, a pig with five legs... Had Harry been too dismissive of the idea that souls existed? The existence of Voldemort's Horcruxes was at least weak evidence for them, and it would at least explain why you couldn't Transfigure specific people.

You couldn't Transfigure magical objects, but you could Transfigure something magical into something mundane, so the Stone should cure things like lycanthropy. If magic was based on a marker gene, that probably wouldn't make the wizard into a Muggle.

That was when Harry made the obvious connection.

Wizards were essentially Muggles with magic. They counted as magical creatures, but that was only a genetic thing. It would be entirely theoretically possible to use gene therapy to make a Muggle magical.

You couldn't Transfigure the mundane into the arcane. You could Transfigure all of a Muggle's genes into the exact same boring old chemical DNA, but with the genetic marker for magic - the Blood of Atlantis.

That would at a stroke extend people's lives massively, make them much, much safer... There were bound to be problems, but the number of lives saved would be enormous.

There was no reason the Universe couldn't contain "I-win" buttons like the Philosopher's Stone.

Harry began to grin as the enormity of what had just happened hit him. He'd need to talk it over with Professor Quirrell, but things were looking good for world optimisation.

Harry opened his eyes and looked up.

He was looking at the tip of an outstretched wand.

The wand fell away. "Harry?" the man whispered.

Bellatrix? was Harry's first, absurd thought. The man before Harry was tall and once-handsome, his beard unshaven and his hair long, but his eyes were dark and hollow, and he looked prematurely old, and thin - as though he'd been emaciated once, and never quite recovered. Yet his wand was perfectly steady, and he bore an air of danger and power that Harry had come to associate with powerful wizards.

And that was when Harry's brain finally made the connection, the conversation with Hermione that felt a lifetime distant. Harry looked directly into the eyes of Sirius Black.

Do not react. You are an innocent little boy who has never seen a picture of Sirius Black before.

"Who- who are you?" Harry asked, tingeing his voice with nervousness.

"Oh, Harry," said the man, looking at him with strange, sad fondness. A note of confusion coloured Harry's mind. "You look just exactly like your father. But with your mother's eyes..."

Black trailed off, looking exceptionally uncomfortable, like he wanted to say something but had no idea how to. He sat down heavily in a padded chair that hadn't been there a moment ago.

"You knew my father?"

Black pressed his bony hands over his eyes.

"Oh yes. It was my fault, Harry, I'm sorry, I as good as killed them..."

Can we ever have a conversation that's not cryptic? asked Gryffindor.

Black took a deep breath. "My name is Sirius Black. I was your father's best friend, and he named me your godfather."

Within himself, Harry barely flinched at all. His parents hadn't been perfect, hadn't been omniscient, he knew that well enough. On the outside, he looked appropriately horrified.

Black winced. "I know, I know what they all think about me. I didn't do it, Harry, not deliberately." He pulled up his sleeve, revealing a bare arm. "I wasn't the one who showed Voldemort where your parents were hiding." His voice hardened. "It was Peter."

"Um," said Harry, "what?" Pettigrew was the one almost all the conspiracy theories blamed... it wasn't wrong just because the conspiracy theorists said it, in fact, if anything it was very weak evidence that Pettigrew really was to blame, but even so...

Black sighed, and conjured a chair for Harry. "Peter is a Metamorphmagus, he can change how he looks, and he used that in the war. He was working as a spy, and he turned it against us." In the dim, non-magical lamplight, Black's skin looked grey. "He came to me, asked where James and Lily were hiding. Please, Harry, understand that Peter and I had been friends for years. I thought he would have died under the Cruciatus before telling Voldemort anything. Like a fool, I told him, and..."

Black's voice trailed off.

OK, could this be genuine?

Complexity penalty, said Ravenclaw. The problem is that actors this good are rare... probably not that rare amongst Death Eaters, though...

"So, um, Mr. Black, how did you end up being blamed, then?" Innocent-Harry enquired tentatively.

"Just Sirius, Harry." Sirius withdrew a bar of Honeydukes' chocolate from his pocket and offered some of it it to Harry, who refused politely.

"James and Lily were killed, and I..." Black seemed to be struggling to get the words out.

"James and his family, they took me in - my own House disowned me because I wasn't stupid enough to hate Muggleborns. And Lily brought out the best in James, once he'd grown up a bit, she was like a sister to all of us. I don't know what else you've heard about them, Harry, but they really were some of the best people you could hope to meet."

Sirius took a bite of chocolate.

Harry was feeling strangely warm, like he hadn't quite felt since that day in the hallway with Severus. I'm tentatively saying genuine, said Slytherin. Perfect Occlumens...es? Occlumentes? Are rare, and this doesn't sound like a lie.

Motivated cognition, said the Inner Critic.

"Peter came to me, disguised as an Auror I knew fairly well. He said he'd tracked Peter to a Muggle neighbourhood. I was too angry and hurt to think straight, and I followed him. He'd kidnapped someone, fed them Polyjuice to look like Peter, bewitched them to shout about how I was a traitor. We were both Disillusioned, and he changed into me, dropped his Charm, and blew half the street apart before I had time to think."

"How did the real Peter escape, then?" asked Harry sceptically.

Sirius stood up abruptly and blurred into a large black dog, then back again. "Your father, Peter and I were all Animagi." Sirius' expression grew distant, and wistful. "Have you met Remus, Harry?"

Harry nodded.

Sirius looked carefully at him. "Remus is a werewolf."

"I see," said Harry. That explained a lot, actually - Mr. Lupin was a skilled wizard, and yet his robes were shabby and he drifted from one job to another; those scars on his face never faded. Werewolves were deadly even to some adult wizards, and unable to control their actions once transformed. They were also entirely harmless as long as they took Wolfsbane Potion once a month, which was reasonably cheap, and yet the Ministry didn't provide it for free to werewolves because people were stupid.

"We found that out about him by the end of our first year. Wolfsbane didn't exist at the time, so Dumbledore had put measures in place for him - the Hogwarts wards tracked him, and every month he came to this place," Sirius gestured around, "to transform safely."

Harry raised his eyebrows. "We're near Hogwarts?"

"Yes. I don't know how your scaly little friend over there knew about it, but this is the Shrieking Shack in Hogsmeade. There's a loophole in the protective enchantments on Hogwarts. You can Portkey out through the Shack, but not in."

That made sense. Hogwarts' grounds were big - it had all happened too quickly to notice at the time, but now that Harry looked back they'd come nowhere near the boundary of the wards.

"Remus used to keep all sorts of things as Portkeys - twigs, combs, , and he always panicked when we asked what they were." Sirius smiled fondly. "He honestly thought we'd abandon him, the prat. Instead, the three of us learned to become Animagi - your father was a stag, Harry. Werewolves aren't very aggressive towards other animals, so that way we could keep him company, and be an extra layer of security. We started calling ourselves the Marauders, the greatest pranksters Hogwarts had ever seen."

Sirius's eyes were sparkling. "Speaking of which, I heard about your little escapade with those bullies. Not bad, young Prongslet, but it doesn't measure up to the one where we got McGonagall to- well, I'll tell you another time."

The smile vanished as though it had never been. "Anyway. Peter was a rat, which suited him down to the ground. When he blew the street apart and framed me, he changed forms and ran away just as the Aurors arrived."

Sirius smirked bitterly. "It was the second-best prank I've ever seen."

Silence reigned while Harry tried to digest all of that. It... didn't entirely sound like something a real Death Eater would say, it was too complex, a hardened Dark Wizard would surely just claim they'd been Imperiused or tortured or something. That said, it had pulled his heartstrings perfectly, which was convenient.

Something in Harry felt repulsed at that thought, and it occurred to him again that that might be how he spent the rest of his life - never quite convinced that a smile was just a smile. Harry glanced over at Professor Quirrell. Harry had inherited Riddle's thought patterns and some fragments of memory. Quirrell had inherited an input of Riddle's entire mind. In that moment, Harry thought he might have begun to understand how Monroe had felt on that cold October night.

"So our magnificent justice system threw me into Azkaban without a trial. They never even stopped to wonder why Lucius stood by and let that one happen. And then, one day, while I was sitting there happily losing my mind, Dumbledore broke me out."

OK, this is just silly, said Slytherin. It was plausible until now, but come on. I mean, conspiracy theories are all very well, but this is... what next? Were they rescued by, by Draco Malfoy in a Boeing 747? Did they melt through the steel walls of Azkaban with the jet fuel?

When most people try to make things up, it doesn't sound like this, said Ravenclaw. And unlikely things do happen. Shuffle a pack of cards, and it's probable that that permutation has never happened before...

"Why would Dumbledore do that? How would he even know you were innocent?" asked Harry.

"Apparently, Peter, the idiot, came to Hogwarts in his Animagus form, searching for some cursed object old snake-face had apparently hidden there. Peter was never very powerful. He might have been able to run away and live in another country, but it must have been a bit of a disappointment. He went from a warrior for the Dark Lord to a rat on the run, and he obviously decided to go back to his old ways."

Sirius grinned, a curiously canine expression. "Sadly for him, the Marauders' legacy was alive and well. Your friends the Weasley twins happened to show a lovely little map we'd all made to their big brother Bill, who noticed that his brother's rat was called Peter Pettigrew, and ran to Dumbledore. A couple of Memory Charms later, and Bill was in St. Mungo's, Peter was Confunded to turn into me, and I was free."

I quit, said Ravenclaw.

Harry put his head in his hands. They really ought to start paying me more for all this.

It had been horrible to do that to Bill... nothing like as bad as leaving someone in Azkaban, certainly, and Bill had recovered fully and, the twins had said, was now a curse-breaker for Gringotts.

That seemed like an unusually happy ending, and Dumbledore had shown every indication of caring for his students. Could the entire story of Bill's psychosis be pure fabrication? That should get a complexity penalty, but Harry wasn't even sure that was valid when Dumbledore was involved.

Sirius had been remarkably straightforward with Harry for an adult, and at that thought Harry's respect for him rose several notches. "Sirius... that whole story sounds..."

Peter Pettigrew, by all accounts, had been smart. He wouldn't risk everything to run back into enemy territory - literally into the enemy castle - just to try to get some mysterious thing. On the other hand, Voldemort might well have left orders for his servants to try to retrieve Horcruxes after a given interval of time, just in case his creation didn't quite work as planned. Peter might have further supposed that some other Death Eaters had been given similar orders, and feared Voldemort's retribution if Peter had disobeyed orders...

Sirius gave a bark of laughter. "You're telling me, Harry."

Harry rubbed his forehead, then remembered that he was having a conversation with a man who was either a mass-murdering traitor or his caring godfather. "What have you been doing with yourself?"

A sigh. "Well, the war was done, and Moony- sorry, Remus was the only friend I had left in the world, and he'd spent years thinking I was evil. I knew he'd never forgive me anyway, for what I told Peter." Sirius looked down at his robes.

Harry was about to start talking about egocentric bias and how Remus Lupin wasn't the kind of person who would hold a grudge against someone for one stupid mistake, but then decided to shut up.

Sirius collected himself. "I ended up drifting back to Hogsmeade, and took over Honeydukes as 'Ambrosius Flume.'" Sirius gave an elaborate bow. "Sirius Black, ex-convict extraordinaire, mass-murdering Death Eater and purveyor of delicious sweets to children."

Despite himself, Harry snorted.

OK. This is all starting to look like some kind of bizarre plot, said Slytherin.

Who could possibly benefit? asked Ravenclaw. And why make it this complex? And this... well, this?

That story just doesn't sound right. Pettigrew's plot was complicated and needed extremely precise timing, but it went off without a hitch. It's... it looks like what Professor Quirrell arranged in the corridor. It looks set up.

Harry shook his head, as though to rid himself of the thought. "What are you doing here tonight?"

Sirius shrugged. "I live in Hogsmeade. The wards I put on this place when I was in school triggered for the first time in years, and I was curious."

Who could possibly benefit from Peter Pettigrew framing Sirius Black, then being captured himself, then breaking Sirius out of Azkaban? asked Ravenclaw.

What happened as a result of that? mused Slytherin.

Anyone behind this whole thing would have to be unbelievably good, or cheating somehow. Suppose somebody needed Sirius completely out of the way temporarily, for some reason, but still had use for him.

What happened with Sirius out of the way?

Well, Sirius would have been Harry's legal guardian, and in his absence Dumbledore had become Harry's guardian.

Dumbledore, who had given Harry to his parents.

Dumbledore, who "had some sort of foreknowledge".

Dumbledore, who was more than powerful enough to fake the whole thing, to make the scheme work by brute force.

Dumbledore, who had a taste for bizarre, incomprehensible plots.

Dumbledore, who understood the phoenix's price more than well enough to leave a friend in Azkaban for a few years.

Harry stayed silent for a moment.

"Look," said Sirius. "I know it sounds strange, and you're probably right not to trust me. Merlin knows your parents shouldn't have. But I'm not a Death Eater, Harry, not in a million years. Expecto Patronum."

A silver dog burst from the end of Sirius's wand, tail wagging.

Genuine or not, we still shouldn't trust him, murmured Slytherin.

Harry rubbed his temples in a circular motion. He wasn't in any immediate danger. He could afford to take a minute to be tired and confused and elated and horrified and not thinking straight.

Harry was starting to wonder if the universe was deliberately messing with him specifically.

"Good evening," came the dry voice of Professor Quirrell.

Author's Note:

A/N: clues about the Mirror puzzle, which I now realise was probably much too hard:

1. Even Quirrell can't fool the Mirror. It's something he genuinely wants to do.

2. It's something to do with the fact that the Stone (unlike in HPMOR) can perform otherwise-impossible feats of healing, up to and including, for instance, healing the Longbottoms.

3. It involves a backdoor Dumbledore programmed into the Mirror, in case he or an ally, for whatever reason, desperately needed the Stone for some specific purpose. Dumbledore doesn't know what the Stone does. He has, however, read enough books to not seal away the Stone completely, especially when it comes to the most salient purpose that he has in mind.

Chapter 9: Shut Up And Multiply, Pt 2

Professor Quirrell was on the defensive, now. He had held off Baba Yaga and Perenelle before, but even he had his limits.

Riddle was more powerful than he had been before. David Monroe had spent his decade alone in space planning new spells and rituals, consolidating his grasp of power, and now Riddle had somehow surpassed him despite having been conscious and sane for under a minute.

He really should have thought of this.

He'd recognised, of course, that this plan would be absurdly risky.

But "risk" meant very little to David Monroe, what with his Horcruxes and certain other special measures he'd taken.

This had obviously all been set up in advance in some manner. He didn't have time to think who the mastermind might have been.

Possessing Granger probably hadn't been part of the plan, so Riddle must have a backup body... and yes, Baba Yaga had drawn something from a hidden pocket and cast it to the ground, and a too-tall man's form lay still on the ground, glowing faintly blue. Breaking the possession would be pointless.

There was an Anti-Apparition Jinx up now, which he could trivially break if he weren't, in fact, fighting for his life.

Riddle ran beneath him, inhuman speed more than making up for his lack of broomstick bones, and David barely deflected a wave of wrongness that turned space in on itself and sucked the magic out of the air.

Even Dumbledore wasn't this powerful.

And he made the obvious connection. Riddle had somehow gone to the Flamels and arranged this, and the price he'd asked for, in exchange for retrieving their Stone, was all their hoarded lore...

David's wand was almost knocked out of his hand by the next wave of magic. He was tiring, fast.

Harry was under his Cloak, and if he had something up his sleeve, it wasn't helping David now.

He had no allies yet living who could meaningfully aid him.

Harry was wearing the True Cloak of Invisibility. He had broomsticks and emergency Portkeys. If all else failed, he was connected to the Horcruxes. The boy could look after himself.

Winning this battle was not on the table, but he'd planned for this eventuality, just in case, because there was no "too paranoid" when it came to Voldemort. He might be able to defeat the Dark Lord, if it came to a Second Wizarding War, so long as he still held the Philosopher's Stone.

Lose.

Without warning, David shot up into the sky like a bullet from a gun, weaving airtight shields around himself, inclining to the side and out of the range of the Jinx, and finally vanished with a soft pop of Apparition.

OoOoO

The Dark Lord has returned. Professor Quirrell cannot stop him. He will take the Philosopher's Stone and tear apart everything you know. He has Hermione's body and the magic of a troll and unicorn. He has over a hundred Horcruxes.

Solve.

... Harry couldn't think of anything Professor Quirrell wouldn't already have thought of.

What can I do that he can't? What can I do that he wouldn't?

Tom Riddle has a severe known bias: systematically failing to properly consider other people.

Harry looked at his Patronus.

He closed his eyes and willed it to listen to him: go to Professor Dumbledore and tell him this: the Dark Lord has returned. Come quickly, with help.

The Patronus vanished.

Sirius seemed to have fallen to magical exhaustion, and Quirrell was fighting alone.

Harry looked up and saw Professor Quirrell fly high, high into the sky and Disapparate, and his stomach sank. No, no, no...

Albus Dumbledore burned into existence in all the fury of his wizardry, Snape, McGonagall, Bones and Moody about him.

And the Dark Lord turned and blasted him with a curse that broke Dumbledore's rapid counterspell with a mighty crack, and Dumbledore stumbled back with his face showing raw shock.

THINK! Harry screamed at his brain. Quirrell had taken the Stone and fled, but if Harry left now, he would leave four people to die - and maybe Dumbledore too, if Voldemort and Baba Yaga and Perenelle combined could overcome the wielder of the Elder Wand.

The Order of the Phoenix fanned out, setting themselves behind Dumbledore, raising their wands.

The Dark Lord held his wand casually in Hermione's hand, smirking.

"It was foolish of you to come here tonight, Albus," said Tom Riddle with Hermione Granger's voice, in an entirely uncaring tone that Hermione herself had never once used.

Dumbledore might have been mistaken for a statue.

Hermione's lips curled into a smile, and Voldemort gestured to the two at his side. "Your friends the Flamels were very forthcoming with their secrets, you know."

Dumbledore did break, then, and his gaze flicked between Baba Yaga and Perenelle with a terrible comprehension, and the Dark Lord laughed.

Harry was reminded horribly of the feeling when he'd finally put two and two together and guessed that Professor Quirrell was Lord Voldemort.

"Nihil supernum," said Dumbledore, and nothing more.

OoOoO

Minerva stood beneath the moonlight, keeping steady control over her breathing.

Riddle did have a flair for the dramatic - unless that's another mask - but that wasn't the only reason for this delay.

Most offensive magic made some sort of sign, some sound or light or tangible sense of magic that might actually be significant in a duel this close. There might be other subtleties to consider, with the sort of Interdicted magic Albus used.

It seemed hopeless. Minerva didn't understand what was happening, but if the Flamels had joined Voldemort she doubted even Albus could triumph.

I see you still look to others to save you.

David Monroe had said those words to her, and after the useless indignation had faded, she'd mulled them over.

What can I do, personally, to make a difference?

Transfiguration, came the obvious answer.

Minerva hesitated. Using Transfiguration in combat was, was...

Was significantly less dangerous than letting Lord Voldemort live.

She couldn't match Albus in skill, but perhaps there was something even he wouldn't think of...

She could not afford - no, the entire world could not afford for her to be squeamish.

She looked hard at the enemy, and tried to think like Harry Potter, look for some Hufflepuff bones to sharpen.

Voldemort was shielded already, naturally, nothing outside the shield. That wouldn't stop anything Dumbledore cast, but it would slow down lesser magic and mundane forces. Albus Dumbledore was no pureblood supremacist - he had heard of such things as sniper rifles, and Voldemort had adapted accordingly.

The Flamels, then. Albus had told her they were not accustomed to interference, knowledgeable but lacking the insight that was essential for a powerful wizard or witch to make best use of eldritch lore. They were certainly not used to combat, if Albus had ever known them truly.

And that was no lie. Perenelle Flamel was fidgeting ever-so-slightly, hadn't even removed her cloak yet, the sweeping fabric trailing far away from her.

She was powerful and deadly. But she was not a Battle Mage.

Minerva considered the form and substance of Perenelle's cloak, the interwoven cloth fibres that composed it.

She could theoretically take one of those threads and pull it out.

One couldn't Transfigure part of an object - at least, she couldn't - but one could Transfigure an object that so happened to be touching another.

Like, say, one of the threads of a cloak.

Minerva extended her magic, steadily, subtly, whilst Voldemort taunted Dumbledore.

The Dark Lord would certainly notice such an... unusual attack, sense the trace of magic. But a witch who hadn't duelled in half a millennium?

The time taken to Transfigure something into a target is a function of its volume and that of the target form.

Minerva Transfigured a thread of the cloak into a loop of razor wire.

Beneath the moonlight glints a tiny fragment of silver, a fraction of a line...

And Minerva Transfigured the loop into another, identical one, one hundredth of an inch across.

(black robes, falling)

Blood spills out in litres

Minerva cried Finite and ended the magic, even as Dumbledore and Voldemort clashed together in a burst of red and green light, and somewhere in the background a too-adult child's voice incanted Frigideiro, and Baba Yaga bellowed and turned her staff on Minerva McGonagall.

Harry had seen the blonde witch fall, and only hesitated the barest fraction of a second before casting the Cooling Charm.

Killing Curses streamed from Baba Yaga's staff towards Professor McGonagall, but they burst into nothingness against Harry's Patronus.

Dumbledore's wand was a blur of grey, and he was flying low over the ground, held up by Fawkes. He was throwing everything he had at the Dark Lord, but he was too busy trying to shield the others from Voldemort, Harry could see.

Moody was already stumbling, and Bones didn't look much better.

Voldemort gestured, and a burst of balls of fire hissed at all four Order members. Dumbledore evoked a wall of purple light that sustained the impacts, but was sent staggering away by the bolt of sickly yellow that drilled through it. Dumbledore began to say something, but the infant spell shattered under a beam from Voldemort's wand.

Baba Yaga was holding off all four of Dumbledore's allies together. Battlefield control, Professor Quirrell had once said, was a Battle Magic speciality, and Voldemort exemplified it.

What deadly powers can I access? What force multiplier can I use?

Voldemort didn't have his broomstick bones. If he didn't have the Order to protect, the mobility afforded to Dumbledore by Fawkes could help... but it probably wasn't enough...

...And if the Order left, Voldemort and Baba Yaga could both concentrate force on Dumbledore. Defeated in detail.

Harry had recognised its dark side for what it was, and he was employing every last instinct of Riddle's to find some weapon to bring to bear on his progenitor.

With Voldemort's aid, Baba Yaga had cut off Snape and McGonagall from Bones and Moody.

Harry realised with a jolt of panic what was going to happen an instant before it did.

A curse from Baba Yaga winged towards Professor McGonagall, passed cleanly through Harry's Patronus.

Snape was already there in front of her, a Shield Charm on his lips.

And Voldemort leapt up, five metres or more, over Dumbledore's head, and ripped away Snape's shielding.

The Potions Master made no noise as he fell, a hole punched cleanly through his chest.

Harry raised his wand and formed once more the words of the Cooling Charm-

And Voldemort blasted Snape's body to ash and dust, because as far as Albus Dumbledore knew, a dead body wasn't worth worrying about.

OoOoO

It should have had more gravity, that moment. Severus Snape was dark and brooding, complicated and mysterious. He wasn't supposed to just die like that. It just wasn't appropriate. His death, if it happened at all, should be poignant and dramatic. He should have leapt in front of Professor McGonagall and pushed her to safety, not sort of awkwardly ended up in the path of the curse meant for her.

He should have looked finally at peace in death, maybe whispered Lily Evans' name one last time, not collapsed in an undignified heap and then been cremated by Voldemort.

The Dark Lord was not stupid. He had seen what Harry had done when Perenelle died, and spared a curse to stop Harry from playing the party Cleric.

Harry could see it all unfolding. Perhaps the Order could still flee, but he didn't see how. Even if they could, Voldemort wasn't playing games any more. Magical Britain might not have hours this time, let alone years.

Harry had never known Snape well, but he had given his life and his happiness in service against Voldemort, stood for decades against the darkness, for all his flaws.

Intent to kill.

In the cold light of Tom Riddle's dark intelligence, the battlefield faded into a series of possible weapons, the emotional shock of Snape's death muted.

What is unusual about this place? What won't he anticipate? What can kill Lord Voldemort?

Professor Quirrell's voice in his head replied: some sort of truly greater, insurmountable magical effect, such that the world would be forever without the Dark Lord...

What is lost to Dark Rituals cannot be regained.

Harry Potter froze in horror.

Why, yes, yes there was something here that could kill the Dark Lord.

The Dark Lord who was in Hermione Granger's body.

Please, no...

Overruled, spoke the voice in his mind of... of Albus Dumbledore and Professor Quirrell and Mad-Eye Moody and Draco Malfoy and Slytherin and Gryffindor and Ravenclaw and even Hufflepuff and Hermione Granger herself.

But they weren't voices in his mind, they were all just him, just different ways he could think, and there was just... simply no way that Harry could think that gave him a different answer.

Harry reached down and touched his wand to the sacrificial circle Quirrell had drawn. The Philosopher's Stone had left it not just permanent but nonmagical. Breaking the shape of the circle wouldn't break the magic, because there was no magic.

He was empty and sick and he thought he might be crying, but he wasn't trembling, and his mind was still clear.

Hermione had been his best friend from the very beginning. His first friend, in fact. He had gone to extreme lengths to protect her. He had looked at Lucius Malfoy and the Dementors of Azkaban and Death itself, and refused to let any of them touch Hermione Granger.

But he was not the only person who felt like that about someone else. How many people would die, if it came to a Second Wizarding War? How many would feel exactly how Harry had?

That's not an apt comparison, protested some final part of him, weakly. Those people might still be retrievable, they aren't going to be SACRIFICED TO DARK RITUALS-

Shut up and multiply.

Harry Potter knelt beneath the moonlight, tears streaming down his face, and began to Transfigure the sacrificial circle around Hermione Granger.

OoOoO

Author's Note: If you have any ideas for how Harry could get Hermione out of this, I would very much like to hear them.

Chapter 10: Shut Up And Multiply, Pt 3

Harry Potter knelt beneath the moonlight, tears streaming down his face, and began to Transfigure the sacrificial circle around Hermione Granger.

And that was when Harry realised he was being silly.

The note, after all, had told him to go back in time five hours, not six.

Voldemort was a blur of colour, and the Order had fallen in on itself, Dumbledore doing his best to shield the rest from Voldemort whilst they held off Baba Yaga, but it was not tenable. One misstep could kill all of them. If Harry failed...

What would I do if I were Lord Voldemort?

If for some reason he had to abandon Hermione's body, he wouldn't just fly away and leave Baba Yaga to her fate. One doesn't become a Dark Lord by throwing away powerful allies, not when one is fighting David Monroe. No, Voldemort would simply possess the Transfigured backup body and keep right on fighting. He had nothing to lose.

Am I sure of that?

Even if there was only a tiny chance that Voldemort would flee...

Harry looked down at his watch, noted the time.

A scrap of parchment appeared, reading simply, "YES".

Harry grinned fiercely. A wave of powerful relief swept over him that none of the Order had thought to destroy Voldemort's backup body. They probably just assumed it was another of Voldemort's victims.

Next problem: how do I get Voldemort out of Hermione?

Harry couldn't hope to get close to Voldemort. He'd be cursed to pieces before he got within five metres. He doubted he could hit Voldemort with a spell, when he was moving that quickly.

So, Harry had to hurt Hermione enough to exorcise Voldemort, but not enough to kill her...

Harry reached into his pouch and signed three letters with his fingers.

Unfortunately, Harry had learned, a handgun was not the ultimate wizard-killing weapon. Of course, a bullet moved faster than most spells, but it was only in films that gunshot wounds killed human beings instantly - and wizards were significantly tougher than Muggles. Barring a very lucky shot to the brain, a wizard of Voldemort's calibre could trivially heal any wound most weapons could inflict. This, of course, was assuming that your enemy didn't enchant some item of clothing with a Shield Charm as an obvious precaution. And, for that matter, that they weren't a troll-cum-unicorn moving faster than you could see.

Harry felt a sense of doom around Professor Quirrell, a legacy of the Riddle-imprint that made Quirrell almost count as Voldemort. That was as nothing to the sense of pure horror, the physical pain in his scar, around the true Lord Voldemort.

Harry was fairly sure that the resonance would be stronger, too.

Harry's lips curled into a tight smile.

Harry had one hour remaining on his Time-Turner - more than enough to cast his Patronus, enlist Professor Quirrell's help.

And so Harry reached into his pouch and withdrew the gun Fred and George had acquired for him, loaded with a bullet carrying a simple Tracking Charm, made permanent by the Stone, the gift of his future self.

Some time in the future, Harry would Transfigure the surface of the tracking bullet into itself.

Harry closed his eyes, allowed himself a fraction of a second to take a deep breath-

Harry aimed roughly at Hermione and fired.

The Transfigured metal and Voldemort's shields shorted each other out. The bullet carried on inexorably, and lodged itself in Hermione's chest.

Two Tom Riddles screamed horribly, and then Hermione's body collapsed in magical flames.

OoOoO

She'll be fine, that troll could regenerate from losing half its skull.

There was no time to think, no time to notice what the Order were doing; Harry sprinted towards Voldemort's corpse, raising his wand-

Quirrell had explained the ritual to sacrifice a magical creature enough that Merlin's Interdict had allowed Harry to hear the incantation, thuo tei dunamei.

Harry had guessed that the majority component of Quirrell's animal-sacrifice ritual was the circle - there'd been no corresponding flare of doom when Quirrell had said the incantation, so it was probably not a major magical effect.

The sacrificial circle was Transfigured around Voldemort's new body in a hair-thin line.

Beneath the moonlight glints a tiny fragment of silver

Harry fixed his wand on Voldemort, began the chant.

Harry's scar began to burn as Voldemort's spirit returned.

Lord Voldemort would certainly have time to shield himself from any curse. Dumbledore would not be able to kill him while he was down - it might cost him a great deal of strength, but even wandlessly Voldemort could sense and deflect any spell from where he lay.

But for all his power - for all his ancient lore and wandless magic - Voldemort was still a human being. A disoriented human being, used to a unicorn's speed. Even if he'd known what Harry was doing...

There was one brief moment when Tom Marvolo Riddle, terror of all Britain, the most powerful wizard the world had seen in centuries, the Dark Lord Voldemort, was nothing more than a magical animal, a specimen of Homo sapiens with a chunk of marker DNA.

"Thuo tei dunamei!"

Harry pointed his wand at the form on the ground, then slashed it at himself.

Riddle's inhuman face was a mask of terror and fury.

Harry knew exactly how the Dark Lord felt. It was exactly how the imprint of Tom Riddle had reacted in Azkaban, the weakness to Dementors, the all-consuming desperate horror of non-existence.

There was one horrible moment in which a Tom Riddle knew that he was about to die.

...And that therefore he had no reason to avoid the magical resonance.

"AVADA KEDAVRA!"

Harry didn't have time to scream.

Something soft but very fast slammed into him from the side, throwing him clear, and the Killing Curse splashed uselessly against the Sunshine General, pale and shaken but very definitively alive.

And then Voldemort began to wither, flakes of skin cracking and crumbling away, and he turned to dust and nothingness.

I'm sorry, thought Harry. He knew it was wrong, knew it was stupid, knew that Voldemort had caused untold pain and suffering, but...

Harry had destroyed all but a remnant of the Dark Lord.

Harry's vision darkened as his mind was assaulted with more than he could possibly process all at once, all Voldemort's Interdicted lore, his magical abilities.

He would be lying to himself if he didn't admit that that was another benefit of the plan.

Later. Deal with it later.

Baba Yaga spat one final curse, threw up a pulsing white barrier, and fled.

Harry reached wearily up to his neck and spun the Time-Turner once.

Chapter 11: Shut Up And Multiply — Aftermaths

Tick. Whistle. Hiss. Hum. Pop.

Harry sat in Professor Dumbledore's office, feeling more... blank than anything.

Now what?

He felt as though he'd run out of road, like the world had come to a sudden jolting stop and he hadn't. Quest complete.

Harry closed his eyes and breathed deeply.

What do I need to do now?

It felt strange, sitting here while the world bustled happily on. Voldemort was gone, unmade forever. Severus Snape had fallen in battle - Harry felt a rush of sadness at that - but he knew that that was an amazingly low price to pay, to prevent another Wizarding War.

Forget the future, what are my immediate priorities?

Harry was still trying to sort through his final inheritance from Voldemort. He needed to research how magical power worked at some point. So far, he felt bigger in some undefinable way. He was fairly sure that that was the feeling of the large "pool" of magical power he'd inherited from Voldemort, but cursory experiments (he'd tried snapping his fingers to conjure a banana again) hadn't worked.

Hermione had been taken to St. Mungo's. They would find nothing wrong with her - only Fiendfyre could hurt her now, with her unicorn blood and troll healing and a Patronus burning bright inside her.

Perenelle Flamel was in his pouch, cold and Transfigured into a diamond. For all that she had more blood on her hands than Voldemort ever had, Harry couldn't in good conscience let her die. It would also be useful to see if she knew anything interesting.

Of course, that would require the Philosopher's Stone, which left another problem.

Professor Quirrell, Harry reminded himself again, was not a good person.

Harry had been incredibly irrational when it came to Professor Quirrell. Looking back, he could apply terms like "motivated cognition" and "Halo Effect", to explain - or excuse, if he was going to be harsh - why he hadn't noticed that the Defence Professor of Hogwarts was a sickly, slowly-dying victim possessed by the spirit of a far more powerful Dark wizard, but at the time...

Harry was going to have to be a lot more cautious and a lot more introspective if he wanted to survive, let alone succeed.

He was going to have to look at everyone and see them clearly - without his own prejudices getting in the way, without Tom Riddle's fatal habit of seeing other people as, well, NPCs.

And he also couldn't afford to idolise people, especially not homicidal Dark wizards.

Nihil supernum.

And so Harry sat and considered David Monroe, as he knew him.

Quirrell was sensible... if he valued human life at all, it was not absolutely unreasonably optimistic to suggest that he could be persuaded to surrender the Stone, so long as Harry swore to give him access to it. If not... Quirrell wasn't invulnerable.

As for what Quirrell wanted...

Quirrell wanted to live, above all. On one level, that desire was effectively granted by virtue of the Horcruxes, and Harry had no power to threaten it.

That said, Quirrell had been worried that Harry might destroy the world, and all his Horcruxes with it.

Harry took little comfort from the Horcruxes. Even if the measures against things like torture and Obliviation Quirrell had spoken of applied to Harry as well, Harry was sure he could find some way. Harry needed to start taking precautions against ritual sacrifice...

Albus Dumbledore appeared in a flash of fire.

You will be polite, said Hufflepuff. You will now be sensible. You will not lash out at the most powerful wizard alive just because Tom Riddle didn't like him.

Harry looked carefully at the Headmaster.

Albus Dumbledore had fought a war against an enemy who simply outmatched him, and it had almost broken him. He'd carried on nonetheless, because there was nobody else. He knew better than anyone the hero's burden.

Harry had been a fool not to re-evaluate the Chief Warlock, when it became clear that he was sane. He'd been a fool not to tell him what he knew. Dumbledore was wise, and he was good.

Nihil supernum.

And yet, for all that, Dumbledore still thought that death was the next great adventure. He still had decided not to investigate the Philosopher's Stone, probably because that had seemed like something Voldemort might do-

Harry winced as Dumbledore punched cleanly through his Occlumency barriers, flicking quickly through his memories.

The Headmaster raised his hands apologetically. "I am sorry, Harry, but I had to be sure Lord Voldemort had not taken control over you."

And make sure you got all the Flamels' lore from me, Harry thought but did not speak aloud.

Headmaster Dumbledore sat down heavily. He reached over and scratched the top of Fawkes' head.

"Congratulations are in order, naturally. Well done, Harry."

Harry shook his head slightly. "I shouldn't have had to do that to anyone. And Professor Snape... I made a promise, when..."

Dumbledore looked gentle, but measuring. "Tell me, Harry. What was going through your mind, when you faced Voldemort? When you saw that he was winning?"

Harry looked down at the desk. Your anger with Dumbledore is the anger of a dead man. Your reasoning is artificially impaired.

"I needed some way to kill him permanently. It wasn't until after I thought of the ritual that I realised it would kill Hermione as well."

Dumbledore sighed, and all at once he looked like an old man again.

"I do not wish to mar your triumph, Harry, but-"

"I'm not stupid, Headmaster. I-" Harry cut himself off and took a deep breath. "Let me start again."

Harry closed his eyes, composed his thoughts.

"I am sorry, Professor Dumbledore. Some things I've said to you in the past were... unfair. Vindictive. Frankly, cruel. Voldemort hated you, and so..." Harry trailed off. "I did listen to what you said after the trial. I knew about it even before then. I was going to sacrifice Hermione to kill Voldemort, Legilimise me if you don't believe me. I just... thought of something better."

Dumbledore's gaze remained stern. "You did not know. Even with the Time-Turner, you did not know. Your future self might have lied to save Hermione. You still do not comprehend the magnitude of suffering-"

Professor Dumbledore had stood, and turned towards the direction of his Phoenix Price room.

"There was a Plan B."

Dumbledore halted.

"Voldemort's magic couldn't touch mine. The effect was worse for him - it killed him once." Harry smiled grimly. "My Patronus thought is something I can desire to share with anyone, even Voldemort. Plan B was to summon my Patronus and tell it to follow Voldemort. He'd never be able to return properly again, and we'd be able to track him down and sacrifice him if he ever tried."

Professor Dumbledore was staring at him.

"You... weaponised the Patronus Charm."

"I'm not a psychopath, I'm just very creative."

Dumbledore sat down in his chair even more heavily.

"Ah," said Harry, "that reminds me, actually. Now is probably the time to tell you what the Philosopher's Stone actually does."

Professor Dumbledore nodded. "Master Flamel only ever hinted. I thought it unwise to pry..."

Harry suppressed another flash of irritation. Prying into secret magic gets you killed. Dumbledore had no reason to think "Flamel" was lying.

"The Elixir of Life is a myth. The Stone makes magic permanent. And it can heal people, heal damage modern magic can't, things like... well, like Cruciatus damage."

Dumbledore flinched. "He lied, for all those years... kept it away from the world..."

"I don't suppose," Harry said, not wanting the Headmaster to lapse into more regret, "you have any idea why one object would make magic permanent and cure brain damage?"

Harry wasn't even sure that that reasoning was valid at all. He lived, after all, in a world of magic. For the first time, the terrifying thought was starting to occur to him that maybe the world just didn't ultimately make sense.

"As I said, I know very little of the Stone, Harry. I have, however, just now been trying to rectify that gap in my knowledge." That explained where Dumbledore had been.

"There are references, scattered ones, to the Stone of Alethiontology, the Stone of True Being. I had thought it mere legend, but it seems likely that the Stone in fact has only one effect: to render any substance, magic or indeed person the true thing. How that is determined, I cannot say; still less, how it is brought about. All I will say is that it is at least the second most powerful artefact I have ever heard of."

"Yes. And now Professor Quirrell has it."

"I suppose it would be optimism to the point of foolishness to expect that he would hand it over."

Harry shrugged. "It won't be easy, but if it comes down to it, we might be able to seize it from him. And... maybe, if he could be persuaded that it made me less likely to destroy the world..."

Dumbledore looked at Harry oddly, then.

The old wizard leant back in his chair and rubbed his eyes.

"Harry, it seems you already know something of your... situation. There is something I must show you."

OoOoO

Harry beheld a long stone hall, stacked with shelves, feeling faintly unsettled.

Upon the shelves rested small white orbs, shining eerily in Dumbledore's wandlight. Some of the orbs were polished and gleaming, but others lay beneath the dust of centuries. Somehow, though, they all seemed to belong equally, and there was no trace of any human hand disturbing those shelves to place the orbs.

There was a blurring effect around the orbs and a sort of pressure in his ears that Harry didn't think was part of the magic of the place.

The place was of a magnitude Harry would never have expected. The rows of shelves stretched into the distance - Harry guessed there were at least a hundred.

That seemed unusual, really. How many wizards in Britain - no, let's assume it's the whole world, so a million. We don't know how rare Seers are, but people seem to accept it as plausible that there'd be one or maybe even two in Hogwarts, so say one in a thousand. Seers never make many prophecies in a lifetime...

This place must have been ancient.

"This," intoned Dumbledore, "is the Hall of Prophecy, Merlin's gift."

Dumbledore withdrew from his robes the device of the Chief Warlock, the Line of Merlin.

"When our war against the Dark Lord was failing, for all my magic, despite all the Order's efforts, I came to this place and did what no other had done in recorded history. I invoked an old password and listened to every prophecy recorded here. I learned that Voldemort was the least of my worries."

Dumbledore gestured expansively. "This Hall is perhaps Merlin's greatest feat. There are hundreds of thousands of prophecies recorded here, from all over the world. Many of them are connected, and many of them are already averted. I have not listened to all of them, but all those I have heard point ultimately to one thing."

Dumbledore placed a withered hand on Harry's shoulder. Harry realised he was holding his breath, and released it.

"This world is ending, Harry. Again and again, prophecies foretold the end of all life. Whenever I heard one such prophecy, I terminated its line of possibility. Whole shelves of prophecies I averted, whole lines of foretold tragedy I circumscribed, with a well-placed word or spell."

Professor Dumbledore's gaze was fixed on Harry. "And then came your prophecy, Harry. By rights, I should have ended your possibility, prevented you from ever being born. You will end this world, Harry. That much is inevitable. Whether that means merely life as we know it, or this planet, or all existence, I do not know."

Quirrell was right. "Then... what..." Harry trailed off. If he was going to end the world - why hadn't Dumbledore killed him-

Dumbledore smiled, and there was a gleam of something like triumph in those sapphire eyes. "In your case, your case alone, there is the slightest of loopholes. You, Harry, shall end the world, not life. I do not know how you could do it, but you have ever been blessed with more imagination than I. You may yet rescue this world's peoples, though their home may be doomed."

Well.

I suppose it could be worse. We still have Dumbledore and Professor Quirrell and Hermione...

Harry suppressed a shudder. Something didn't feel right about this whole situation - which he supposed was fitting.

Dumbledore shook his head, as though to clear it. "And that is what I have dedicated my life to. That has been the ulterior motive behind... oh, at least nine parts in ten of my apparent madness. At the bidding of prophecy, I crept into your bedroom while you slept and administered the Sleep-Cycle Potion. I gave your mother Lily the means to help your mother Petunia, ensuring you would grow up surrounded by science. I used the Ventriloquism Charm to tell you to look for Hermione. When you were very young I cast a Reductor Curse at the rock on your windowsill, and to this day I still do not understand why."

"You killed my pet rock!"

Harry had found his voice at last, and that was what he'd blurted out.

Dumbledore chuckled.

Harry cleared his throat, ears burning slightly. "Can I hear these prophecies?"

"No. They are very clear that you must never hear them. I have heard all the recent prophecies that have not been already averted, Harry. They are of no further use, that much is clear. To that end..."

Dumbledore raised his wand and cast a spell Harry now recognised as Enai's Greater Destruction.

Thousands upon thousands of glass orbs shattered, the legacy of Merlin lying in fragments upon the floor.

A mass of ghostly Seers arose, and for a brief moment the innumerable voices sounded like the roar of a jet engine even through the Charm on Harry's ears.

Then Dumbledore flicked his wand, and the images and glass fragments vanished.

The Chief Warlock raised the Line of Merlin Unbroken and touched it to the wall. There was no visible ceremony, no bangs or flashes or puffs of smoke, just a quiet sort of dying feeling as though someone had suddenly unplugged a television that had been on, unnoticed, in the background.

"And so we face the future unknowing, as it was before Merlin."

The two wizards burned out of existence, leaving only the silent shell of the Hall of Prophecy.

OoOoO

Professor Quirrell appeared in the dark street without a sound, and drifted into a slightly run-down cottage.

Inside lived amongst the most esteemed of magical historians, but she was old, withdrawn. She was into her third century, ancient even for a witch, and slowly dying. The Healers' arts were failing them more and more as Merlin's folly eroded wizardkind, and nobody still living could coax such damage to heal. Still, her magic was with her, and she refused all offers of help.

The Death Eaters were long since disbanded, and they had never been suited for such work as this. David was no fool. Riddle's little habit of underestimating other people had killed him, and it was time and past time for David to learn from his mistakes.

If he was going to save the world, it might be nice to have help. Prophecy was far from understood, but the best place to start might be here.

Nobody would be suspicious about the "death", not with a perfectly realistic corpse courtesy of the Stone.

"Somnium, Legilimens," Quirrell said to the sleeping form, extracting all the fragments of old lore, all the knowledge of influential people that the great historian had ever accumulated.

It was the work of a second, to sweep his wand over the sleeping woman and fix the Transfiguration with the Stone.

"Innervate".

The woman sat up in bed, gasping, and it took her a moment to realise that she wasn't in any pain.

"Good evening, Ms. Bagshot," came a cool, precise voice. "I have a proposition for you."

OoOoO

There was quiet, for a time, back in Dumbledore's office, save for the constant noise of the artefacts in the background.

"I'm sorry," Harry eventually said again. "All this time, Professor, you were the sane one... the only one doing the right things for the right reasons..."

Dumbledore shrugged lightly. "I long since ceased to care what others thought of me. Life has far fewer headaches that way."

He grew serious again - sombre, even. "Harry, in truth, I did not expect to survive Voldemort's downfall. I did not expect you to deliver us another miracle, to end Voldemort so soon. I am gambling literally everything on you, now. This is, as I'm sure you need no convincing, of quite literally the utmost importance."

Dumbledore reached into his robes for the Line, and passed it unceremoniously to Harry, without hesitation.

"Merlin's legacy is yours. Do not uphold it. Surpass it. That is your burden, Harry. I give you everything I have - the Line, leadership of the Order, all such resources as I can command. I will gladly share any fragment of lore you require. If you can find some way to overpower me somehow - preferably without killing me, if you wouldn't mind - to take the Elder Wand, do so. Your survival is imperative."

Harry took the Line.

Nothing visible happened. Merlin had not shared the Peverell's more ostentatious excesses.

The Line did not grant its wielder any secret magical powers. It simply granted them control over the Wizengamot, and let them monitor the Department of Mysteries, and opened certain very interesting vaults...

It didn't allow the Chief Warlock to break the Interdict, not even with the world at stake. Merlin had planned millennia in advance, and the Line could not tell what its wielder would be inclined to do.

"Merlin, you idiot..." Harry muttered.

"Come again?" asked Dumbledore, one eyebrow raised.

"The Interdict. It stopped people from ending the world with dangerous magic, but it didn't have any measures built in in case people needed powerful magic to prevent some other threat."

"What would you have done instead?"

"Used the Mirror," Harry replied promptly. "It shows your coherent extrapolated volition. If I'd made it, the Interdict would censor powerful magic unless you stood in front of the Mirror and it showed you not ending the world."

"Alas," said Dumbledore. "Even Merlin did not consider everything." He steepled his fingers. "I cannot, at present, conceive of any means of lifting the Interdict, but that does not mean it is impossible."

Harry yawned, the events of the day finally catching up with him.

"I doubt you will have time to lead the Wizengamot, and frankly it is a bureaucratic nightmare I would not wish upon Voldemort himself. I suggest you appoint me as regent."

Harry nodded wordlessly, and returned the Line of Merlin..

Dumbledore seemed to understand. "My office is open to you, Harry. Come at any time. There is more I must discuss with you, but it can wait. Sleep well."

Harry stumbled from the office.

OoOoO

An infinitesimal fragment of ruby positively glittered with enchantment beneath the microscope. With the slightest spell, it adhered seamlessly to the Philosopher's Stone, and its magic became true.

OoOoO

David appeared before a quarantine room of St. Mungo's hospital. Hermione Granger slept within, next to a box of rats and flies.

Knockturn Alley was home to many who would not be missed. One such individual lay now in an enchanted sleep, floating eerily.

This was absolutely necessary, as even those called good would agree.

What could charitably be called a life ended in a flash of green.

The Dark wizard stood, murmuring the spell of the Greater Horcrux over Hermione Granger.

After a time, a small item disappeared into his robes, and Quirrell and his victim vanished as though they had never been.

There was a resigned sadness across the nation the next morning, when it was found that Bathilda Bagshot had died peacefully in bed.

Nobody noticed the disappearance of another nameless petty criminal.